A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Division, Program Area One FA572
Rockefeller Archive Center
The restructured Foundation comprised two programmatic divisions led by vice presidents: U.S. and International Affairs Programs (USIAP) headed by Susan Berresford; and Developing Countries Program (DCP), headed by William Carmichael. Berresford had been at the Foundation since 1970, coming from the U.S. Manpower Career Development Agency. She served in the National Affairs area, first as program assistant and then program officer (1972-1980), becoming head of women's programs in 1980. The main international efforts under USIAP were housed in Rural Poverty and Resources, Human Rights and Governance, and International Affairs. The other programs - Urban Poverty, Education and Culture, and Program-Related Investments - also addressed a scattering of international issues related to their main themes.
Carmichael had joined the Foundation in 1968 as Representative in Brazil. In July 1971, he was named Head of the Office of Latin America and the Caribbean, and in September of 1977, he became Head of the Middle East and Africa Office. The DCP program was responsible for all the Field Offices: Andean and the Southern Cone, Brazil, Mexico and Central America, Bangladesh, India, Southeast Asia, West Africa, Eastern and Southern Africa, and Middle East and North Africa.
When the Foundation initiated a Human Rights and Governance program (HR&G) in 1981, it was the first instance of a Ford program explicitly entitled "human rights," despite the fact that human rights grantmaking that had started officially in 1976. International Affairs remained separate from HR&G. In 1987, however, the Board conceptually linked three programs, creating a Trustee committee called Human Rights, Governance, and International Affairs, which existed until 1992. Operationally, however, the programs relating to these fields did not often work together.
International governance remained a commitment under Thomas. The Foundation, for example, had a long-established relationship with the United Nations: from 1951 until 1988, the United Nations received ninety grants from the Foundation (it received another 198 over the period 1989-2009).
In these early years of the Thomas presidency, dramatic changes were occurring in the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe. Under President Mikhail Gorbachev's leadership since 1985, the USSR was opening up to the international community, the rule of law in society was taking prominence there, and press freedoms were spreading. The foundation developed new programs in the region, drawing on the $60 million already spent to promote human rights and free expression and increase Western understanding of developments there.
Given the continuing economic constraints facing the Foundation and rising debt in developing countries, the Foundation shifted support under DCP to smaller scale community-based initiatives in the field offices. Thomas was also charged by the Board to increase the diversity of grantees, especially to favor populations "most affected" by the problems of concern to the Ford Foundation. The Foundation built on earlier efforts and sharpened its focus on women's issues throughout the world, including shifting the focus of the population program to women' reproductive health and child survival.
In the 1980s, Carmichael and others, with strong support from Thomas and the board, continued the 1970s' support of South African grantees for training large numbers of black lawyers and litigating sensitive cases in the South African legal system. Recognizing the multifaceted nature of discrimination in South Africa, the Foundation not only advanced the rule of law, but also strengthened civic organizations, women's groups, and educational institutions. Further, it supported a number of activist organizations in the United States that were energetically advocating US governmental sanctions against South Africa and for private disinvestment. The Foundation also played a role in shaping US policy on apartheid through the role Thomas played from 1985 to 1987 chairing the US Secretary of State's Advisory Committee on South Africa.
The Foundation's overseas staff also sought to improve the economic situation in poor, marginalized communities through targeted loan programs particularly to women head of households, beginning with the innovative work in Bangladesh of Professor Mohammed Yunus, the founder of the Grameen Bank. The results led the way to establish the field of microfinance with the aim of empowering women living in poverty conditions, such as through a microfinance network in Latin America starting 1980 and a global lending program for women starting in 1987.
Thomas encouraged staff to share results at worldwide meetings. During those meetings, Ford staff in the country offices and in New York tried to follow the mandate to work as "one foundation." The persistent challenge toward meeting that goal, however, was that initiatives emerging from the New York-based programs, or indeed any program developed in one country, were not always adaptable, relevant or acceptable in other countries or regions. It remained a challenge to develop a unified program, despite the commitment at the highest level of foundation leadership.
Biographical / Historical
Segment 3. Period Summary - Transition and Restructuring 1966-1988
During this era, the Foundation's earlier interest in business and the economy evolved into a commitment to improving conditions for people living on the margins of society. The Ford Foundation promoted advancements in women's rights around the globe and introduced micro-lending into grantmaking. At the same time, the economic issues that were shaping program strategies also affected the Foundation's assets. Severe cuts resulted in a significant restructuring of country programs and reduced budgets across all programs.
Even with the cuts in country offices, in the 1970s Ford grantees in developing countries received approximately 80% of the International Division budget. The remaining fifth went to Population, Development Studies, and International Affairs. Although representing a much smaller piece, the International Security and Arms Control program from 1973 was the Foundation's most concerted effort to make meaningful inroads in disarmament and nuclear issues - those challenges most directly linked to the Foundation's historic concern for peace. By 1979, the Ford Foundation was the biggest funder of arms control as a field, both in the U.S. and overseas.
- Field Office Files, 1957-1970; I
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of correspondence, memoranda and reports from the Foundation's overseas field offices in Latin America and the Caribbean and South and Southeast Asia. The Foundation's operations in India are particularly well documented.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Census -- 1970 Round of National Censuses -- Memoranda, Background, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - English as a Second Language (ESL) Final Report, Feb 1964 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ford Foundation -- Grants in Overseas Agriculture -- Report, Memoranda, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ford Foundation -- Policy Issues -- Reports on Ford Foundation Activities, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ford Foundation -- "Responsibility for International Activities" Memorandum, Jan 29, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Fox, Melvin -- Ford Foundation Foreign or Second Language Activities, 1951-1966, May 1967 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Latin America and Caribbean (LAC) -- Bell, Wilheim -- Trip Schedule and Background, Feb 1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Latin America and Caribbean (LAC) -- Caribbean Program -- Self Study, Sep 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Latin America and Caribbean (LAC) -- Cost of Living Tables, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Latin America and Caribbean (LAC) -- Ford Foundation Mission to Mexico Report, Nov-Dec 1964 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Latin America and Caribbean (LAC) -- Housing Allowances -- Memoranda, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Latin America and Caribbean (LAC) -- Travel and Study Manual, [1969] (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Manitzas, Nita -- Proposed Grant Information, Paper on Fellowships, Budget Request Information, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - South and Southeast Asia (SSEA) -- Bangkok Office -- Correspondence, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - SSEA -- Educational Consultants for the Southeast Asia Program -- Memoranda, FAP, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - SSEA -- Harvard-Pakistan Planning Commission Study Committee Reports, Mar 1962 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - SSEA -- India -- Economic Aid and Development -- Reports, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - SSEA -- India -- Education -- Memoranda Re: Resource Base, Background, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - SSEA -- India -- Education Commission -- Members List and Bios, Correspondence, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - SSEA -- India -- Ford Foundation Assistance -- John Bresnan Statement Before International Technical Cooperation and Assistance Panel, President's Science Advisory Council, Sep 23, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - SSEA -- India -- Foreign Training Programming -- Memoranda Re: Potential Funding of PhD Study-Related Travel Costs, May 12, 1965-Feb 15, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - SSEA -- India -- History of Foundation Activities Report (separated), Feb 1966 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - SSEA -- India -- Inter-Uterine Devices -- Correspondence Re: Delivery and Distribution, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - SSEA -- India -- Travel and Study Awards -- List, Memoranda Re: Commitments, 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - SSEA -- Indonesia -- English Language Programs -- Report, Correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - SSEA -- Indonesia -- Reference File -- Correspondence Re: Coup and Aftermath, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - SSEA -- Indonesia -- Ramparts Magazine Article Re: Berkeley Mafia and Indonesia Massacre and Ford Foundation Response, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - SSEA -- Karachi Office -- Correspondence, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - SSEA -- Karachi Office -- Correspondence Re: Litigation, etc., 1967 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - SSEA -- Kuala Lumpur Office -- Correspondence, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - SSEA -- Kuala Lumpur Office -- Correspondence, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - SSEA -- Manila Office -- Correspondence Re: Bangkok Visit, Clipping, etc., 1967 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Melvin Fox Subject Files, 1953-1967; II
  These files document the Language Development Study project of the International Training and Research Program. The files contain a copy of the ITR report by Cleon Swayzee, with related memoranda and comment letters.
  - International Training and Research (ITR) Program -- Swayzee, Cleon O. -- Comment Letters, Internal Memoranda (1 of 2), 1953-1967 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - International Training and Research (ITR) Program -- Swayzee, Cleon O. -- Report (2 of 2), 1967 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Language Development -- Background Papers (1 of 2), [1967] (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Language Development -- Background Papers (2 of 2), [1967] (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Language Development -- Correspondence Re: Language Study, etc., 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Language Development -- Foreign or Second Language Activities Report, Conference Papers, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Herbert Passin Subject Files, 1957-1966; III
  Mr. Passin's subject files primarily pertain to his work as a consultant and expert on Japan. Other files document the Foundation's grant-making activities in China, Korea or Tibet.
  - American Assembly -- U.S.-Japan -- Notes, Correspondence Re: Wada Zentaro, Aug-Sep 1966 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Asian Conservation Laboratory, Inc. -- Fellowship Application, Reports, Background, 1960-1963 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Bereday Teachers College -- Japanese School -- Reports, Reference (Japanese), 1964 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Chuo University -- Correspondence Re: Grant Request, Background, Jun 25-Jul 16, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Ekvali, Robert B. -- Tibet -- Correspondence, 1963-1964 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - English as a Second Language -- Meeting Notes, Transcript, Background, Mar 30, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Glueck, Sheldon -- Correspondence, Background, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - History of the Ford Foundation's International Affairs Program, Dec 3, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Hong Kong -- Chinese University -- Memorandum Re: Ford Foundation Support, Mar 18-19, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Hong Kong -- Grey, Robert -- Correspondence with Colonial Secretary G.T. Rowe, Jan 1964 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Institute of International Relations -- Japan-Inoki -- Correspondence Re: Proposal, 1964-1965 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - International House Meeting -- Japan -- Memoranda Re: Ford Foundation Support, Wealth of Japan, Oct 30, 1964-Oct 12, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Japan Center for International Understanding -- Kosaka -- Memorandum, Oct 1, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Japan Parliamentary Exchange -- Memorandum, Correspondence, Background, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Japan Program -- Basic Dockets, Memoranda, 1963-1966 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Japan Program -- Memoranda -- Re: Japan Trip, Philippines and Korea, Illustrative Projects (1 of 2), 1962-1963 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Japan Program -- Memoranda -- Re: IA activities, Japan projects, etc. (2 of 2), 1964-1966 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Japan Socialist Party -- Correspondence Re: Study, May 13-Jun 7, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Japan Society -- Japanese-American File -- Arts Program, Jun 17-18, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Japan Trip -- Itinerary, Priorities, Memorandum Re: Ford Foundation in Korea, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Kiyosato Educational Experiment -- Rusch, Paul --Correspondence Re: Farm School, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Korea -- Memoranda, Notes, Background on Assistance to Taiwan and Korea, 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Kosaka -- Japan Council for International Understanding (JCIU) -- Correspondence Re: Trip, Organization, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Labor Movement in Japan -- Karsh, Bernard -- Memoranda, Background, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Mancall of Harvard Translation Project Re: Japanese and American Scholarship on Communist China, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - McCray, Porter -- John D. Rockefeller 3rd Fund -- Correspondence Re: Arts in Japan, 1963-1964 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - NHK (Japan Broadcasting Corporation) Educational Television -- Correspondence Re: American Educational TV Exchange with Japan, Mar-Sep 1963 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Passin, Herbert -- Japan Trip Notes, Dec 1963-Jan 1964 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Reischauer, Edwin (Ambassador) -- Correspondence Re: China, Jan-Apr 1963 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Rose, Elizabeth -- Correspondence Re: Proposed United Nations University in Asia, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Russian Studies in Japan -- Robert Byrnes Report (separated), 1960-1964 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Rutgers University -- Correspondence Re: International Conference on Japanese-American Cultural Relations, 1962-1963 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Seki, Yoshihiko -- Study Abroad Candidates, Aug 27, 1962-Nov 4, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Slater, Joseph E. -- Notes on Hong Kong Discussions on Proposed Chinese Federal University, etc., Nov 1-6, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Slater, Joseph E. -- Notes on Japan, Oct 25, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - St. Paul 's University -- Rikkyo -- Correspondence Re: Research on Postwar Japanese Economy, 1962-1965 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Stone-Passin Japan Trip -- Itinerary, Memoranda on Ford Foundation in Japan, Background, Mar 1962; Passin, Herbert (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Stone, Shepard -- Travel and Study Awards, Items for Discussion, etc., 1957-1963 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Tamagawa Gakuen University -- Correspondence, Background, Dec 26, 1962-Jan 10, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Tobata Proposal Re: Japanese Modern Agriculture -- Memorandum Re: Applicability to Asia and Joint IA-ITR Funding, Oct 7, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Travel and Study Awards -- Eisenstadt, Samuel -- Correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Travel and Study Awards -- General Lists, 1963-1965 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Travel and Study Awards -- Procedures, Dec 1, 1964-Feb 12, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - TV Exchange -- Louis G. Cowan Summary and Recommendations Re: American Educational TV Exchange with Japan, Feb 5, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Von Briessen, Fritz -- Correspondence, Mar-Apr 1963 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Washington, University of -- Modern China Project Proposal, 1961-1963 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Yomiuri -- World Conference on Peace, Tokyo and Kyoto, Japan -- Correspondence, Background, 1963-1964 (Box 6, Folder 15)